♪ [music] ♪
[announcer] Welcome to the 38th
annual NBA All-Star game
from the Chicago Stadium.
[crowd cheering]
[people chattering]
[announcer] ...a little timeout
to reorganize
and the chances of a West comeback
are slipping away...
MacGuire for three...
I have never seen an All Star game
that had such a spectacular passing
and plays and thundering plays like these.
Aw, what a way to end this ball game!
Right now I wanna, you know,
play in the NBA like anybody else
would wanna be,
that's something I dream
and think about all the time, you know,
playing in the NBA.
He's just doing something
that he loves so much!
He just loves it so much, you know,
I'm just happy for him.
If somebody can understand the way
William plays,
that'd make me feel
a lot better, I'll say,
they should've understood the way
I played.
[announcer] He's making his seventh
All-Star appearance,
6'1'', Isiah Thomas!
When I get in the NBA,
I'm...The first thing I'm gonna do
I'm gonna see my momma.
I'm gonna buy her a house
and I'm gonna go down and make sure
my sister and my brother's okay.
I'm gonna give my dad
a Cadillac Oldsmobile
so he can cruise into the game.
[Arthur's mother] He dreams about it.
He looks at those basketball commercials
where they'd be advertising
like these Nike shoes
and he tells his small brother:
"Joe, Joe, that's me."
I don't even think about it, you know,
if he don't make it.
Because I'm so, you know,
focused in on him making it.
I just know he'll make it, you know.
♪ [music] ♪
I'm off to Central
and the Cars Expressway.
A park over there where there's
a pretty talented young man.
Earl Smith works downtown
as an insurance executive.
On weekends he's an unofficial
talent scout
for several area high-schools.
This is what you call
"beating the bushes."
This is the job of most of
your freshman coaches
and guys like me who played a little bit
of the game,
who love trying to help young people
on the road to success.
Today Earl spots Arthur Agee,
who just graduated from grammar school.
He got the first step...
I will bet you a steak dinner
in four years you'll be hearing
from him,
and I don't even know
anything about him.
Several days later, Earl takes Arthur
and his family on a recruiting visit
to the high school where
NBA star Isiah Thomas played.
The visit will give St. Joseph's coaches
a chance to see Arthur perform.
Your role today, Arthur,
is to impress the coaches.
Try not to be too fancy,
but take your open shot,
when you have it
play good defense
and make good passes.
Rest of it, just play natural, you know.
I'm hoping I'm gonna go
to St. Joe...and play.
But first I gotta get my books straight
and hopefully come out
and impress the coaches.
[cameraman] Is it kinda scary?
Yes, it is.
I've never been to a school
way out before
and I would be going to a school
with different kids, different races.
You can look at the scenery,
new friends to meet.
[cameraman] What if Isiah's
there today?
Wow! If he be there,
I'd be shocked,
cuz that'd be my first time
ever seeing him
up close, in real life.
Basketball has to be second
to your academics.
If you don't get your grades
you're not gonna play.
If you work hard at the grades
and if you work hard at basketball,
then I would be able to help you
as far as going to college.
And I guarantee this.
I can't promise you where you're
gonna go and if you're gonna be a star,
but I guarantee that I will help you get
into the school
that would be best for you.
I'm making a commitment to you
if you make a commitment to being part
of this kind of a program.
Out of all the kids at the St. Joseph
basketball camp,
there are a few like Arthur that
coach Pingatore is recruiting.
[Arthur] It was like a million of guys
trying to be better than the other,
but to me, I was better than all of them!
Except Isiah.
It's been a great pleasure to
introduce you a graduate of St. Joe's,
high school All-American
All-American from Indiana University
5-time NBA All-Star,
Isiah Thomas!
[crowd applauding]
In everybody's neighborhood,
there's a guy who can really play,
who can shoot the lights out.
Every time down the court.
Then he goes to St. Joseph high school
and the guy gets cut!
You say: "Tom was real built,
why did he get cut?"
See, Tom didn't learn
the fundamentals of team basketball,
which is what you're learning
how to play.
He told my dad that he knew
I could play,
so he just had to play me hard.
[Pingatore] I can see
the playground in him.
I can see talent,
but I don't see the confidence.
When I faced Isiah, I just knew
he was gonna be a great one.
He had that total combination
of personality, confidence,
talent, intelligence.
I think I see it in one kid
that's coming here.
He flows with a smoothness
and confidence
and strength that you don't see
in every kid.
He could become a great player.
I just bang him and bruise him.
I'm trying to let him know right now,
you're gonna get hit,
you're gonna get knocked down,
you're gonna get banged around!
So you better get used to it now.
[Curtis] All these
basketball dreams I had...
they're gone.
All I see, all my dreams are
in him now.
I want him to make it so bad
I don't know what to do.
[William's mother] If they wanna
play basketball and stuff,
that's always okay.
But I always made sure all of them
got through high school.
A high school diploma was
very important to me.
[William] Our mother, she is like
mother and father to me.
She won't let me really
hang around over here that much,
'cuz of the gangs.
I feel if I go to St. Joseph,
I'll at least get a good chance to
go to a good college.
That would be good for me.
[William's father] That was my
first son.
He's daddy's man, you know,
so we just started calling him Man.
I could've been a good college player,
I'm...most likely I would've made it
to the pros, you know?
But, you know, once I had my son
I knew then something good
was gonna come out of it.
I think the talent's gonna be passed on.
He told me, he said:
"I'm so scared of growing up."
I said, "Why?"
He said, "A grown-up has
so many problems,
I got so many things on my mind!"
I just want our Arthur to have more,
you know, have a better life than
what I had.
I don't want him to experience
the bad things
that I went through in life, you know?
[Conductor] Austin Blvd will be
the next stop, Austin is next.
Like Isiah Thomas before them,
both Arthur and William make
a three-hour round trip each day
between the city and St. Joseph's.
[Arthur] Those planes when we're
going out through our file at school
I saw a rug, flowers, clean hallways,
things that I didn't see at
an ordinary school.
Arthur wins the starting
point guard position
on the freshman team.
[Pingatore] Agee, I want you to find
that warm-up number 2!
Round, number 3! Etmeier, 4!
Hey Arthur, hey man!
Hey you know if you miss a free throw,
they count them up
and you have to pay 15 cents!
And then if you don't pay it
they gonna make you
fifty lashes and you still got
to pay the money!
You still gotta pay the money?
That's the way out!
[Pingatore] When Arthur first started
at St. Joseph's, he was a good kid
from what we saw,
but he was very immature.
He might have been
a little more disruptive,
speaking out,
getting into childish things.
He wasn't used to the discipline
and the control,
he reverted back to maybe his
environment, where he came from.
I just have never been around
a lot of white people
and it was different because
at a black school you know I could
associate with the people that was
you know, they talk the way I talk.
It's a little hard but I can adjust to it.
[Pingatore] You can see
there was talent there.
We kept saying up in the stands:
"Get the ball to Arthur because
he's going to do it for you!"
and sure enough, they gave him the ball,
with seconds on the clock.
[Sheila] I've noticed a change immediately
after he started going out there.
To see your child mature you say:
"Ah, well maybe this is good for him."
William begins his freshman season on
St. Joe's Varsity,
the top-ranked squad in-state.
[cheering and applauding]
He's already received several letters
from Division I schools,
Marquette, Rice, and Creighton,
Illinois State to name a few.
You're killing us!
Why did he get to the ball before you?!
He asked me, do I wanna be
a great player?
And I keep saying "yeah."
He said: "For four years
I'm gonna be on you every day",
so he said: "You might as well get
used to it now."
Hard left...no, no.
Go hard left!
Right I know you can do it,
left you can't.
Go hard!
Not bad. Do it again!
[students chattering]
[bell ringing]
[Teacher] If you look at Matthew,
and again he's saying:
"At the time, the kingdom of Heaven
will be like this",
This is how Matthew's gonna use Jesus,
this is how he's gonna start it out.
What this is saying is
that you have to take the faith.
[Arthur] When I first came down here,
I was like: "Boy, I wanna go home...
Is this really the right school for me?"
But every little thing you do,
that go against their rule
you have a detention
and they'll suspend you quick
at the school too!
They'll suspend you quick.
The kids that are willing to do it
are gonna take something away that
will help them for the rest of their life.
The kids that are not willing to do it
for whatever reason
are not gonna be very successful
as far as here.
[Teacher] The civil rights movement
started up in the 50s...
When William first entered St. Joe's,
tests revealed he was working on
a fourth or fifth grade level.
I could see that he had the potential
but because he was shy it seemed as
though no one was trying to reach him.
[William] Sister Marilyn told me,
"You have to be one good ball player
to get in this school with these grades."
At the end of the year
he had gone four grades above
just in the way he listened and learned.
[William] Back in grammar school,
academics really didn't matter too much
to me at all.
It was playing ball for the team that
really was like the stand-outs
in the school.
We showed up in class,
that was good enough for them.
I was just going to school for the girls,
trip out with your friends,
get out, go play
some more basketball!
That was basically it.
Arthur also entered St. Joe's on a
fourth or fifth grade level.
[Arthur] I don't think nobody
in their right mind is crazy about school.
If the president brought up a thing
right now to say "Close all schools",
do you think any kids would be
trying to go out there,
stand on the picket line and wave,
and get billboards saying:
"Reopen schools?"
Arthur was in the lower group
of the general program.
At the end of the year he was still
in the lower group.
For Arthur, the season is over.
His freshman team finished second
in the conference.
William's varsity is rolling
through the playoffs.
Against Proviso East,
William plays his best game yet
and the Chargers move a step closer
to going downstate
to compete for the title.
St. Joe's made it downstate
5 of the last 6 years.
[Pingatore] The one thing we haven't
done is win a state tournament.
[William] Man, it'd be a big thing if
I go downstate as a freshman.
Isiah was good enough to start
on the varsity as a freshman.
I didn't do it because I was
worried about being moved too rapidly.
I think by not doing it,
it cost us the state championship.
In the sectional finals,
Fenwick challenges St. Joe's title hunt.
But in the second quarter,
William steps up.
With his brother Curtis looking on,
William scores 16 points to lead
the Chargers to the sectional title.
[announcer] From Chicago,
it's The Sports Writers on TV!
I think I may have seen
the next Isiah Thomas.
St. Joe at Westchester has a kid
named William Gates
who is starting as a freshman.
Remember you heard it first
from Bill Gleason.
Put it in your memory bank,
ladies and gentlemen!
Put it in your memory bank, okay!
- William Gates.
In the super sectionals,
St. Joe's meets de Sales to decide
who will go downstate.
William plays more like an intimidated
freshman than a freshman sensation.
6'9'' senior All-American Eric Anderson
dominates St. Joe's.
But in the third quarter,
William takes over again.
He fires over Anderson,
and is fouled.
William's 13 points in the second half
pull the Chargers to within 4.
With less than 2 minutes to play,
it's a must-score.
St. Joes' jumpshot falls short.
[crowd cheering]
Despite the loss,
William's gutty performance
bodes well for next year.
[math problem]
Who wants that problem?
Try it, William!
[correct answer]
Very good!
When I went out there I was
very intimidated cuz I just knew
that everybody out there
was just smarter than me.
As the year went on
and I was making
the A and B honor roll
I just felt like:
"Hey, I'm just as good as them".
And now what you have to identify...
Both William and Arthur have
partial scholarships from St. Joe's.
The rest of William's tuition is
paid for by Cycle,
a Cabrini Green organization,
but Cycle can't cover
this year's tuition increase.
I was called on
by brother Edwin DuPray
He was trying to raise money
to help kids that couldn't otherwise
go to those kinds of schools.
It really touched a soft spot in my heart
and so I decided that my husband and I
would participate on a personal basis.
William was selected as the kid that
was able to go to school
based on our contribution.
Nice to see you.
You played a great game!
With continuing support
from Patricia Weir,
William is assured that his entire
education at St. Joe's will be free
Arthur's family is paying for
half of his tuition,
and the increase comes
at an especially bad time.
Work for Sarah Lee got laid off
work for Scholar's meatpacking
got laid off then, you know?
You look around your house you see
your food getting low, okay,
and you know you got your
bills due here, your bills due there.
I had got called down to the office.
Brother Leo wanted to talk to me
and he was telling me about how much
certain money my momma had to pay
for me to stay in school.
And they said,
if she don't have it by this time,
you gotta stay out till she pays it.
And I was staying out like
two and three weeks and stuff.
- By the end of the freshman year,
whatever balance there was for tuition
was never taken care of.
Consequently going into
the sophomore year
we had the balance plus the new tuition
so that it was going to continue
to become a problem.
We have a scout that they have
come out to the different neighborhoods
and scout out these little basketball
players and get them to come
to their school and offer them
this scholarship.
Then once they get out there,
the story is totally different.
I was under the impression that
Arthur would have help
for getting to his school.
Arthur would have help in
getting his books.
Arthur would have help in--
But see, none of that occurred.
Finally, with the Agee's owing
1500 dollars in back payments,
St. Joseph's forced Arthur
to leave the school.
I thought Pingatore and them would
help me out but...
You have to draw the line
because as I said,
tuition is something that as school
we depend on
for 90% of our revenue.
I guess he thought I, you know,
I wasn't gonna be
that big of a ball player, so why would he
just waste some money on me
staying there?
Or you know, he thought
I wasn't gonna grow.
He kept on saying like, "when you
gonna grow?" or something like that.
Well I don't know.
If I had known all of this was
gonna lead to this,
Arthur would've never gone
to St. Joe's.
I mean if I had known
that he was gonna have to go through
this type of pain
and myself the anguish of it,
and then to put him out
in the middle of the school year.
♪ [music] ♪
[bell ringing]
[students chattering]
Arthur is accepted at the public
high school near his home.
He's been out of school for two months,
and lost a whole semester's credit.
Here you have a youngster caught
in the middle of two
separate school systems.
Had he stayed at St. Joseph's,
he would have been able
to receive credit for that first semester.
Doesn't seem fair but then
that's the system.
If he's going out there and he's playing
like they had predicted him to play,
he wouldn't have be at mercy,
economics wouldn't have had anything
to do with him not being in St. Joe's.
Somebody would've made some kind
of arrangement
and the kid would've still been there.
He's not making it like they thought
he was gonna make it
on the basketball court,
so he's not there. Simple as that.
And it doesn't take no brilliant person
to figure that out.
It's mid-season when Arthur joins
the sophomore team.
He was so depressed and devastated,
he just closed himself off in his room.
And I would go in there
and I would tell him every day:
"Hey, things'll look up".
Coming off the bench,
Arthur wears number 11,
Isiah Thomas's number.
[teacher] What kind of techniques were
being used to take away the freedoms,
that had been earned? Okay.
Arthur?
What other techniques were used
to keep black Americans from voting?
You could almost forget about
he's being there.
That's how quiet he really was,
and I think the transition had
something to do with that.
And comparing Marshall High School
to St. Joseph.
I don't think that there was
any comparison.
People can afford to send
their children there.
They can afford to put money
into the school.
Once they walk in those doors
they walk in there to get that diploma
and go on to college,
whereas our students if they
get out of high school a lot of them,
it's an accomplishment.
If he wanna go back next year,
he's gonna go back if I have to beg.
Because then what would happen with
his little dream?
Arthur's mother Sheila has lost her
minimum wage job as a nurse's assistant
because of chronic back pain.
It's just a real hard area
to live in...period.
As far as raising kids...
Kids don't even have a playground,
a play area,
anything constructive to do
in the neighborhood.
But you see why half of them
become gangbangers, and you know,
because it's nothing constructive
in the neighborhood for them.
So now it's just like you know you more
or less got to keep your kids close to you
and watch them at all times.
♪ [music] ♪
In June, after 20 years of marriage,
Arthur's dad leaves the family.
They say, you look at how many
shots have been taken.
To look at my shoot on,
15 out of 40.
15 out of 40?
I'm just saying... He done it.
If you do that,
you gonna know about it.
I always tell William,
the most important thing is
getting the ball in the basket.
Coach said the boy's good.
He said he's real good but
he said he don't listen.
He said if he listened to him
he'd be better.
He's always telling me: "You should
do this and you should do that!".
Everybody I know is my coach.
I know a whole lot about basketball.
I guess in so many ways I feel like
I'm a pro at that in my mind.
When he went to college
and like when Michael Jordan first
came to the NBA, there were
no sit around and I would...
...who could play the best.
[crowd cheering]
Curtis was named Player of the Decade
at Colby Junior College,
but he also developed a reputation
for being uncoachable.
Curtis's idea of being real good is
"you don't follow the rules,
you do what you wanna do".
Curtis finally signed
at the University of Central Florida,
but he didn't get along with
the coach and rarely played.
Even if he didn't play ball,
it was a nice University.
He could've finished school
but he couldn't handle it.
Security.
I'm used to everybody
in the neighborhood loving me
and knowing how good I could play.
Just seeing how people looked up to
Curtis Gates when I played basketball
but now just a regular old guy
on the street now.
[announcer] Welcome to
the Prep game of the week
in the Class AA sectional final.
Gates...Good.
Point.
WIlliam Gates is one of
the premier sophomores--
William scored 17 points
in the first half
as the Chargers looked to
return to the state Finals.
[crowd cheering]
Gates...good!
Can they get it done here now--
In the second half, Gordon Tech turns
to their own sophomore star.
Gordon Tech hangs on to a slender lead
in the waning seconds of the game.
My guy's William Gates.
I'd like to see him get it
and just get to go one on one
and just pull up and ice it.
Oh boy, this is it.
Gates has it...he's going to pull up
from way out...Blindsman tips it around...
3 seconds left, Cunnigham goes out
and up...no good! Tech win!
[crowd cheering and applausing]
Congratulations to
the Gordon Tech Rams.
They are on a joyride now
with Champagne.
Arthur's season ended well
and he has high hopes to play
for the Varsity next year.
Arthur's dad shows up.
These days Arthur rarely sees him.
You got old legs dad.
Old legs.
Hey man, I'll see you
later on, ok?
Increasingly, this playground court has
become a place to buy and sell drugs.
Dear Mother, I hope when
Mother's Day comes,
you will light up the sky
with a big smile.
You mother, are the only one
in the world who can provide
and take care of me. You are the one
that makes our family work.
You are the one that I will miss
so much when I go away to college.
No one can replace you ever.
Love always, Man.
Mother's day, 1989.
I said to him:
"What are you gonna do this summer?"
and he said, well, he didn't know.
So I said: "Well if you need a job, let me
know and I'll see if I can help you."
We had a job that didn't require a lot
of previous training, so we hired him.
I messed up so bad on my first day,
that I wanted to do everything right.
I just messed up everything.
Putting tapes in the wrong numbers
and all sorts of stuff.
I just push myself to come out here
because I know in the long run,
it's gonna be good for myself
and for my family.
I give my mother 50 dollars
out of my checks.
All she done for me, I don't think there
will ever be enough to pay her back,
unless I make pros then I'm pretty sure
I could pay her back.
I drew on these, with my man.
Tuss!
I had heard that his nickname
used to be Tuss
and I just started calling
myself Tuss.
You know, I said: "Man, you might not
make it to the NBA".
He said: "Don't be keep on telling me
things like that.
That's just like showing me you don't
have any trust in what I do".
I said: "I do, but don't just keep
putting all everything into this:.
He said: "Well, ain't nobody gonna
take my dream away from me.
That's what I wanna be
and that's what I'm gonna do".
I said: "It's your dream.
What can we do?"
♪ [music] ♪
Dear William,
Georgetown University basketball staff
is very interested in you.
We are going to kick off the season with
a Midnight Madness celebration.
Harvey Mack called,
Michigan State, did they ever call?
Will be on national television.
Any school you name.
Dear William, there's gold at the end
of the rainbow.
500 dollars in there for you too.
[William laughing]
♪ [music] ♪
You see Isiah play?
Yeah, I got him.
How'd you like it?
He played pretty good.
The whole school see me as
being Isiah Thomas.
I'm trying to be my own identity.
When I leave they can be like:
"Oh you're gonna be the next
William Gates!"
Watch Isiah!
Watch him coming!
What did he do?
He took the charge!
Something we have to get
you to do, right?
You listening?
You're actually a better shooter
than Isiah...from the outside.
True!
Because you have a lot of
responsibility, William.
Can you handle it?
I hope so.
I mean going downstate.
You wanna go downstate?
- Yeah.
You gotta do something about it.
You have two years
to get us down there.
And it's gonna be on your head.
Go! Hold up! William!
The man playing defense
ropped way off here.
Now who would you rather
have shoot the ball?
Stow's shooting the ball here,
you stopping here and shoot the ball.
Well, shoot it!
William practices today having
just recovered from a slight knee injury.
Come on!Let's go!
You're playing soft.
William, does it bother you?
Don't be afraid though!
Don't favor it!
Tempo, tempo!
Hold it! That's bullshit!
You didn't jump to the ball
to deny the man.
Nope. Still one.
We'll stay here all day until
you get it in ten seconds.
William, you gotta take it easy.
Go! Go!
Go!
No, we start all over.
You people just refuse to work.
You don't know what it is
to be intense.
If you don't have it,
you're gonna be crap for this team!
Give me a good reason why I should
keep you on this team, Corey!
How about you, Reed?
Give me a good reason!
What do you think, William? I mean,
how many of these people work hard?
Not too many.
- Not too many.
You wanna stay home
when the state tournament comes?
Now go ahead!
[machinery beeping]
The next day in practice
William reinjures his knee.
You most likely have at least torn
this cartilage.
The inside cartilage in your knee.
And you may have a ligament tear
in your knee, ok?
If the ligament is torn, William,
you would miss this year...entirely.
That's a lot to happen to you
at an early age.
But I think if all goes well,
you'll be able to come back.
Everything was just going great...
And now this.
All you guys can't get the high--
Somebody gotta wear a medium.
One of you skinny guys wanna get the high.
Junior Year, Arthur makes Varsity
for the Marshall Commandos.
♪ [music] ♪
Back home, the family's troubles
have worsened.
Now, I'm on welfare
that I wasn't on then.
And trying to live night to night
on something like that is very hard.
And you have three growing kids
that need this and you have bills to pay.
And it's just not enough
to make ends meet.
Man?
Is Man in there?
I was never raised on welfare.
My mother and father, both worked.
We was cut off for three months.
We was cut of complete
with no income.
So therefore,
do you know what happened?
Our lights were cut off,
our gas was cut off.
And we were sitting in the dark.
They had cut me off because I failed
to made an appointment.
It hurt everybody,
it changed everybody's attitude,
that you can have something today
and it's gone tomorrow.
So you know what the system
is saying to me?
Do you know what it's saying to a lot of
women in my predicament?
They don't care.
[machinery beeping]
The good news is that your ligament
looks fine, ok?
Your ligament looks fine.
We can actually sew the cartilage back.
So you're looking at a minimum of
twelve weeks and maybe sixteen weeks
before I let you play ball again.
Possibly being able to play
by tournament time.
Okay?
I'm gonna slip you a little something
into the IV.
Just to take the edge off
of things, okay?
I can tell.
♪ [music] ♪
[medics chattering]
The doctor told me
they weren't even gonna try to
get him ready to play this year.
So you'd think what do you think
they gonna do to his career?
I really thought Curtis was
gonna make it.
But he didn't make it so
I just wanted to try to.
I just wanted this one to make it
♪ [music] ♪
We were able to repair the cartilage.
When basketball is over, William didn't
have a friend in the world.
Curtis lost his job as a security guard
and has been unemployed
for over four months.
Sometimes I sit around and my eyes
just kinda get watery
because I've been like, I ain't amounted
to nothing, you know? I ain't got nothing.
I can't even go out there and get a job
making 7 dollars an hour you know?
I'll be sitting there telling myself,
it ain't gonna get no better?
[chattering]
What did y'all tell me about when
y'all get ready,
you know, after y'all go to college
and everything.
Y'all get your own place.
Yeah. We gonna go to Curtis, baby.
We're not gonna need no food stamps.
- We ain't gonna need no food stamps.
Each day is a struggle.
Trying to deal with the kids' attitude
as well as my own and trying
to be strong enough for them
and myself.
Now that's what you call
a neat paper.
No, it's not.
[men laughing]
What you saying about my son?
My son got a brain. You cut that out!
- That he don't use.
Now there are two new members
of the Agee household.
Arthur's sister Tamika has a baby girl,
named Jazz.
And Arthur's best friend Shannon moved in
to escape his own troubled home.
Shannon's like me. He understood me,
and I understood him.
He could sit back and talk to me
because I was his best friend.
He trusted me and I trust him.
It's been crazy, as far as his father
and his mother's breakup.
He'll come home and bow stealing in.
You know, bad drugs and beat on
his mother and stuff.
♪ [music] ♪
You have to call the police.
Get an order of protection
for him to leave me alone.
My father was the same way.
I'd think about him all the time when
you'd come home and they fighting.
And you know, that gets
to a child's head.
Especially when you living with
your mother and you're young
and that's all you see all the time.
You had to do something
to keep your spirit up.
[crowd cheering]
When I played basketball I knew
what I wanted to do.
This is what I want, you know.
This is what I wanna do
for the rest of my life.
He's way behind where I think he
should be at this point.
I've had a few guys come to me
from college,
ooh, I like that kid.
He's quick he's fast. He's got--
But something's missing with Arthur.
Shannon was on the basketball team too.
He was a little more raw than Arthur is.
Watching them two guys like that.
So I tried the less of the evils,
and that was Arthur.
Marshall's won six and lost 14.
Their worst record in 20 years.
You're just in a hurry to do nothing,
Well, that's exactly what you're doing,
Nothing!
After spending most
of the game on the bench,
Arthur gets another chance.
Just go after that ball, boy! Yeah!
That's the way to go.
In the final minutes of a close game,
Arthur takes it strong to the hoop.
He's called for charging,
and fouls out of the game.
That's a bad call all day.
- Amen!
[metal clanking]
The daily regimen of rehabilitation is
not the only change in William's life.
Say hey!
I was just basically scared
to tell people.
I was feeling sick, you know?
Holding all this stuff inside of me.
I couldn't let it out.
And I did finally tell the coach
and he was like:
"When did this come about?"
And I said:
"Oh three-four months ago".
He was like:
"Three or four months ago?!"
I was in the delivery room,
and the nurses gave it to her,
she handed the baby to me.
I'll never forget how hard she was
squeezing my hand.
Once we got her home, William offered
his help and stuff but it was almost like
I didn't want it cuz I just--
she was mine, you know?
instead of the two of us.
So then after a while I finally
let him keep her.
Yeah, he earned his title.
It felt good.
[baby laughing]
Your numbers look real good.
I think you're two to three weeks away
from being able to practice, full.
Two to three weeks?
I know you wanted to waltz in here today
and I tell you to go back to practice now.
But I don't want it to have to tear again.
I felt that this was the year for me.
♪ [music] ♪
I know I could make it downstate.
That was just a big dream I had.
I look up on the scoreboard,
my name is not even on there anymore.
Where do I fit in with this team?
William takes a make-up exam in math
because he skipped the final.
Here's the cut-off point for passing,
and you ended up right there.
So you passed the final, barely.
When I stopped playing ball,
all my grades just sunk.
I understand we've got
the ACT results.
Yeah.
Not as good as we wanted, huh?
William scores a 15 on his first ACT.
He needs to score an 18 to qualify
for an athletic scholarship
to any four-year university.
I think what we have to do is get you
set up with a the Britannica course.
We'll have to talk to Mrs. Weir, ok?
Sometimes you had the right answer
and you changed it to the wrong answer.
Through Patricia Ware,
William's St. Joe's sponsor,
the cost of the six-week class is waived.
If you're just outright guessing...
if a monkey took this test,
and you trained him to do just As and Cs,
he'll probably get more right than
if you picked As and Ds.
Just done all the fill-in, not knowing
if you're gonna be able to play,
just because of a test.
I mean as soon as you don't tighten
one screw, everything falls apart.
[teacher speaking Spanish]
[Arthur laughing]
What I say?
How do you say "yes"?
Yoy.
How do you say "yes" in Spanish?
Sí.
Look up on the board!
He's a pretty smart kid
but does just enough to pass.
Hey Shannon!
- Most of the men that have come
through here and have had that type of
attitude usually end up on the streets
talking about they used to play
for Marshall. On this class even,
he could have gone to any school
he wanted to, you know?
This is just someone on
the street corner talking.
Trying to find a job,
can't find a job. That kind of thing.
And this where he's headed really.
How's your knee?
- It's great. Yeah.
Easiest thing right now for you
is to play you. Or wait to next year?
What do you want to do?
- Wait 'till next year?
Right.
- No, man.
You think you're ready?
Next year is now.
[anthem playing]
I've seen a lot of kids coming back
from surgery,
where they're worried about
the injury.
When this happens they may never be
the player they were.
William's first start is the final
home game of the regular season.
[referee whistling]
He gotta do that the whole game.
He only do it when they're leading.
It was like my injury is sneaking back.
I always felt that Curtis has now been
living his dream through me.
Hey, you do something out here on
this court. You showed me nothing yet.
You gotta come out and start
playing harder all the time.
Otherwise you're just another player.
You follow me? Just remember what
we were talking. Okay?
As long as you're physically able.
If you're not, you shouldn't
be playing at all.
So Larry was about to start tonight.
I'm glad that I can just get on the floor.
[crowd cheering]
St. Joe's has made it
to the sectionals.
And in the final minutes, William goes
to the free-throw line
with the Chargers leading by 6.
[crowd applauding]
Always a clutch free-throw shooter...
he sinks four straight to help
seal the victory.
In the sectional Finals, St.Joe's looks
for revenge against Gordon Tech,
because they knocked them out
last year.
With his whole family watching,
William seems out of sync
and bothered by his knee.
[crowd shouting and whistling]
At the beginning of the fourth quarter,
St.Joe's leads by a point.
While the doctor examines William's
knee, Gordon Tech surges ahead.
[crowd applauding]
The Chargers steal the ball,
trailing by one.
William calls a timeout.
With only seconds on the clock,
the Chargers find William in the corner.
The shot doesn't fall
but William is fouled.
With 6 seconds to go,
William steps to the line
with 2 free-throws and a chance to win.
[crowd making noise]
He shouldn't be out there.
Shouldn't be playing.
I'm very disappointed.
Disappointed in the system.
He shouldn't be out there playing.
His knee came out of lace
a couple of times, looks like.
If it's not as important,
you'll need to reevaluate the program.
That ain't no excuse, you got out there.
So probably ain't nothing wrong with him.
It's excuse. If he's hurting,
he shouldn't got out there.
There's two possible problems
you can have.
You might have healed let's say 80%
of that cartilage
and still have a small residual tear.
William's brother in-law Alvin,
takes him to see Dr. Hefren,
the Chicago Bulls team doctor.
...arthroscope again.
Here's how we gonna do it.
A lot of people say: "I shouldn't have
played, shouldn't have come back at all".
Coach kept saying it's really up to me,
and leave it up to me,
I'm going back out there on the court.
We're going to remove this
portion of the cartilage right here.
Still will have higher incidents
of arthritis as he gets older
than you and I would,
but in terms of his basketball career,
he has a good chance
of performing fine.
This would be a meniscus.
It's the only thing on my mind,
is getting downstate.
Just making it down there. I want to
be able to go all out, the whole year.
No setbacks.
No nothing.
At least the coach wouldn't have to say
we didn't really play hard this game,
cuz when I step on that floor,
I'll be all business. And that's it.
One year after he left,
Arthur's dad Bo rejoins the family.
He has spent seven months in jail
for burglary
and overcame an addiction
to crack cocaine.
And he tried and tried. Sometimes you're
looking for friends and they're not there.
But Jesus is always there. Even in the
midnight hours, He's there.
Praise the God!
Lord, we know You've
always blessed the family.
Even in the beginning Lord, You've
blessed that first family.
Lord, God, we pray right now,
don't let anything come between them.
Send strength, Lord! Blow, God, away
their weakness!
Please, let the love get to them.
♪ [Bo singing] ♪
While I was incarcerated, I just
asked God: "Show me a different way,
give me a new life,
take the taste of drugs
and the evil way of thinking
away from me".
I asked the Lord to forgive me
for what I did.
The times I mistreat my wife,
beat her physically, you know?
♪ I want to thank the Lord for
protecting my family. ♪
♪ I just wanna say thank you Lord.
I wanna thank the Lord... ♪
I just hope this to be a lesson
to my children, to see me
turn my life over to the Lord.
When I was little, you know,
he didn't let me down.
I figure I didn't make out, that
your father's a drug addict,
your father's on drugs and stuff.
I was gonna be like: "Yeah, OK".
I used to take so much, you know,
that you start realizing, you know,
what was he doing, you know.
Sometimes he was trying to go
to church while he was still on drugs.
He was trying to go to church,
you know?
[Bo and children chattering]
The closeness was not there at first
when I came back to home.
And then Arthur, he was watching me.
What move will I make now,
am I just--
Being like this since I just came back,
am I gonna play bad again, you know?
♪ [music] ♪
William's dad invites him down
to his auto repair shop.
He hasn't lived with the family since
William was a baby.
I was gonna give to you the--
When you're finished up here,
I got you something more to do--
I haven't seen him in like three years,
and it popped in my mind.
Well, that's the car over there,
that black--
I think he's like: "He really was not
been able to play some basketball."
I think in that he sees something
at the end for himself.
He really tried to work me,
but I didn't wanna.
I said: "You maybe my dad...biologically,
but as far as being there...you know?"
You say you'd like to come to the next
show that I do?
Yeah. I'll come out there.
I'll finally get the chance
to see you singing.
Ok, whatever I happen to do, I don't
have my schedules right at this minute.
But I'll have to get that
and I'll let you know.
[William and baby chattering]
I always knew that I was gonna be
a better dad than he was.
I wouldn't just leave her like that.
If Alicia has a problem,
then I have a problem.
[baby chattering]
She's meaning whatever she said.
♪ [music] ♪
William's second rehabilitation is
at the Baxter clinic,
used by many
of the Chicago's pro-athletes.
Both of William's operations
and rehabs
have been paid for
by school's insurance.
Don't expect to be playing in a game
the first day back.
My mother put big restrictions
on Pingatore.
[laughing]
She said: "He ain't hurting
his knees now".
When you're out on a date
you have to have sex.
Oh yeaah. Yes you do.
[students arguing]
For the second straight year, Arthur
and Shannon must take summer school.
[teacher] You state your question!
What I say?
This class is for freshman,
sophomores and juniors
who have failed English.
The basic problem here is that
we were strapped for money
and we've only had one English class
available to our students.
Hopefully you can touch a nerve
of some of them.
Like a spirited discussion
on a controversial topic.
...because exactly,
what is having sex?
But engaging in an act that
doesn't fulfill...does not fulfill--
Shannon didn't really care,
so he just stopped coming
and he was dropped from the Law.
Even if Arthur passes summer school,
he may not graduate
with his class next year.
because St. Joseph's is refusing
to release his transcripts.
I called up the school. The lady
explained to me that he owed $1800,
so I felt that they had
a school policy there
and there's nothing I can do
about that.
About how much can you afford?
We are looking at 18--
- 1310.
Ooh, 1310?
- 1-8-1-3-10.
To total that out...form here
to June...his graduation?
We are looking at
somewhere around...
It's 181,30 per month.
Is there any way possible, that his...
I don't know, I'm just asking,
that his credit be released, too?
I will get a promisory review
drawn up, okay?
As long as you show me good faith
after the first two months,
I will release some, that would be
end of September,
and I'll send them to Marshall.
- Okay.
That would be fine with us
and I really appreciate this.
I was doing it anyway.
It's really good, you know?
I can't really complain about it.
We wish we could have
stayed though, you know?
Well, things happen, you know?
And there's no way to--
It's a part of life.
- I can't let him down, my Man.
Okay, good! I hope we can
work something out then.
I'd like to thank you.
- No problem.
I'm over here trying to help people,
okay?
Yes, right. Alright.
- Okay. Very good.
You have a nice day, Mr. O'Brien.
- Take care now! Okay. Very good.
I think about it,
had I not been on drugs
and Arthur went to St.Joseph's, just
how good it could have been for him.
He wouldn't had to leave.
Here on the corner right here...
here's no corner without a cop.
Out here you see a cop all the time.
They've a lot of money on
these corners but--
I've almost spent my life
along with it.
You can just look at my life and say:
"He's a good example of what not to do".
If he had my ways, I'd be shaking
in my shoes right now.
Look at Georgetown coat, man!
I'm gonna get that.
How much?
- 70 bucks, even. No tax.
Some of the drug pushers
in the neighbourhood,
they give us money and tell us:
"Go shopping and get you something".
They think if we're playing basketball
they can give us stuff
and keep our career going.
That's how I keep up with to start.
♪ [music] ♪
While you're sitting here today,
you should feel like a million dollars.
You should feel so special.
You're one of hundreds of the best
high school players,
in this country, the United States.
My mother, God bless her,
she's in Heaven today,
she has always said to me:
"This is America.
You can make something
out of your life".
[referee whistling]
All the coaches, come over here!
If you're a player, somebody
up there gonna recognize
that you're a player.
There's 250 of us here.
We're doing it to try to find out
who the best players are
and try to get them in our program.
There aren't many kids at any level,
including the NBA,
that really understand
what basketball is all about.
We always say, if you're going to war,
who'd you want behind
to be covering your flank?
If you're rowdy, they'll also
recognize that.
I don't care they may not gonna
write it down in their book.
At the prestigious Nike camp,
William hopes to prove
that the injuries are behind him
and he belongs to the nation's best.
♪ [music] ♪
1-2-3-4.
Arthur and Shannon spent their summer
at Pizza Hut, earning $3,35 a hour.
[clients chattering]
This is a waste of my time.
I'm ready to go home.
Hey, I'm always trying to play
this team ball.
A few coaches...more coaches are
coming around and look.
Everybody feels that they gotta do
their own little thing.
Some of you are gonna make it
what they want to be.
Another of you will not make it.
You'll have a fair chance--
This is summer for them.
They don't particularly like
sitting here in the classroom, but we
provide them with an experience
you can't get anywhere else.
We simulate what it's gonna be like
to be a student athlete.
15 hours a week for basketball.
How many hours we have up here?
Statistics on Division I players
graduating from college
are really frightening.
[teacher] Let's assume you're playing
big time college basketball--
...the real odds. Nobody cares
about you.
You're black, you're a young male
and you're supposed to deal drugs
and mug young women.
The only reason why you're here...
you can make that team win...
and if the team wins,
these schools get a lot of money.
This whole thing is revolving
around money.
Recruiting isn't like any other
sales business.
We've got to win to keep our jobs.
We've got fill the arena
to keep our jobs.
And if we don't, they fire us.
I mean that's--
If bankers don't make money,
they fire them.
Hey look at those young boy's bodies!
They've NBA bodies already.
Already.
One particular kid that's here now.
I've watched him since sixth grade.
I've watched him blossom.
...cuz that's when you want to get
on 'em, when they're young.
And start writing 'em
before everybody else writes 'em.
Try to get it anyway as you can
in this business.
It has already become a mid-market,
but I try to do my job, you know,
and serve professional me.
Which school is most
involved with William right now?
I would say DePaul, Marquette,
Indiana, Michigan--
Excellent!
- Great job! The way to go.
I'm getting-- My best game out here.
I had 16 points, 12 assists. Bo is
going like this: "Hmm".
Yeah, I was smiling too, Bo.
♪ [music] ♪
[players chattering and laughing]
Hey, mom!
Right now I'm just feeling good
about myself.
I always felt like, since I've
been down here, I was All-American.
When I go back home, I'm gonna
feel unstoppable.
I'm gonna pull up on it, okay?
Tell me if it hurts more.
Yeah!
- It hurts more when I do that?
Easy does it!
It's on the muscles, not on the joints,
both the joints, ok?
[referee whistling]
Although it's only a muscle injury,
it's severe enough that
William will not compete
for the final two days of the camp.
♪ [music] ♪
[people laughing]
How many electives do you
need to graduate?
Six.
Arthur's transcript
from St. Joseph has arrived.
If you pass all the classes
that you're presently taking
you can graduate from summer school.
Okay?
Have you taken an ACT?
[Arthur] Um-hum.
When do you plan on taking it?
- Some time soon.
What institution are you planning on
going to? Have you decided that yet?
I was thinking about
going to...Alabama.
But you need
to take algebra 3, okay?
Do you plan to take that?
I don't know.
- You don't know?
So you just barely getting by again?
No, you don't have to say that.
But you are. You've been barely
getting by all along.
You're gonna have to do better
than that if you want to go
to Alabama or any other school.
You gonna have to do more
than just get by.
Don't forget to bring those
papers back to me.
St. Joe's just means everything--
I gotta have more credits,
or they'll keep me out
cuz I ain't paying the money.
That's how I do.
I'll still make it.
Don't let your best opportunity
get away from you.
You can have a great experience
at the Marquette University.
Once you visit our campus, I feel
confident that you'll know
that Marquette is the right place
for you. Sincerely, Kevin O'Neal.
I like this.
I've been getting like two a week
from the schools for...
...for a couple of months.
That is quite a few.
I had Division I offers. I had even
signed with Marquette
because they thought I was going
to make it crazy.
The great ball players, they care
more about basketball more
than they care about school.
And I know they do.
♪ [music] ♪
[tv commentator] If you're looking
for a progressive
college basketball program--
--leadership and a winning tradition,
then the Marquette Warriors are for you.
William's first town recruiting visit,
three top schools postpone visits,
prefering to wait and see how William
will do his senior year at St.Joe's.
If you don't make the test, it doesn't
mean we don't want you,
because we still do.
That's what I'm telling you.
If you tear your knee again this year
and you can't play ever again,
you gonna have your education
paid for at Marquette University.
I know that the scholarship is
one year renewable.
Gene's right about this. But any school
you saw is going to give you four years.
The bottom line is this, we want
to win the national title.
Number two, I wanna make you
the best player I can.
I wanna give you an opportunity
to maybe some day be
one of those guys that goes out
and make some money in Europe
or in the NBA. You're one of seven guys
that we're recruiting right now.
You're recruiting seven guys?
- Seven guys for three spots.
Well, fit him in there.
- Of course he fit in.
As soon as William tells me he's not
looking at any other schools,
then I'm not looking
at any other players.
So what? The first one signing this?
Well, that's what's going
to come down to.
If I tell you: "Hey, you're our guy
and thsi and that",
and I lose you to Kansas, Indiana...
I'm out of luck.
The President's saying to me: "Well,
I thought you were recruiting a guard".
It's a tough situation but it's
something that has to be done.
♪ [music] ♪
It's a great place. We're getting ready
to have you rock it too.
The best is yet to come.
A lot of serious ball players
have been in this building.
Junior Bridgeman, Sidney Moncrief,
Bob Lanier, Oscar Robertson.
Can you see yourself playing
in this place here? 18,000 in it.
Big difference from St. Joe's now.
We stayed at the Hyatt
and it was nice, real nice.
They have these balloons
all hanging up on the ceiling.
They're really geared up.
I'm gonna say, we're geared up...
Room service!
They have all these
phoney newspapers written up.
[announcer] Notre Dame 77,
Marquette 76.
Gates is sky-high calling for the ball,
there are 6 seconds left.
The freshman spins past the defender,
slicing to his left to the foul line.
3 seconds left, Marquette down by 1.
Gates launches a wild one-hander,
it is on the way...
it is...good!
[William laughing]
If you think we care about you a lot
while recruiting, we gonna do more
when you're here, you know that!
Don't let it get to a point, where
somebody else comes in
and takes this scholarship away.
Let us know what you wanna be doing,
unless you know
what you wanna do right now?
What else you want me to say?
[laughing]
Did you talk to any leading black
people on the campus?
The leading black people?
Yeah. Well, whoever may be in charge
of all black citizens on campus.
What kind of community and lives do
they have for the blacks there?
Did you talk to anybody about it?
Did you ask the players
how they were treated?
Yeah.
- What did they say?
Players said they're treated fine.
They get the best of everything.
You think that's where you wanna go?
That's fine.
Obviously if you wait you'll have all
that were on you before
like Kansas, Indiana,
North Carolina State.
Yaa...but I discussed it with--
I think you should take a few days.
Because you just came back,
you understand?
Pooop!
- Yeah!
Yeah!
- Pooop!
Is there any cash with this?
To four years of excellence!
- Yeah.
It's alcohol.
- Not that bad!
I'm fixing him a birthday dinner today.
This is his 18th birthday
and I wanna show him how much
we appreciate him and love him.
and care for him.
Everything that you can imagine
has gone wrong to this time,
but now everybody's together
This is his favorite cake.
He's a great kid. And some kids don't
live to this age, you know?
And that's another thing
to be proud about.
That, you know, this is his 18th birthday,
you lived and get to see 18.
That's good.
I wanna tell you that I love you
very much. I'm very proud of you.
Seems like I was 18 just yesterday.
Here, happy birthday! I love you.
[family applauding]
♪[together] Happy Birthday dear Arthur, ♪
♪ Happy Birthday to you! ♪
Two months after his 18th birthday,
Arthur's cut off from public A.
Here's what I brought to their att--
He's there as a TL task student?
He didn't graduated yet.
So why would you cut him off.
If you'd like, when they get to 18,
most of the black kids, they drop out.
So that means that the child is
just thrown out there.
I was getting 368,
now I get 268.
And that's it. This is to take care of me
from that month to the next.
Now can you imagine a person
living on that?
Do you all wonder some time
how a mother lives on that?
Or how do my children survive?
How are they living?
It's enough to make people really
wanna go out there,
just lash out
and hurt somebody.
♪ [radio] ♪
[shouting on court]
He doesn't play with confidence
like he did before he was injured.
I don't believe the other players
have complete confidence in him.
They were all avoiding him,
when he was a sophomore.
They''re not fond of him anymore.
[basketball bouncing]
Sophomore year,
I was just carefree.
If it could be done,
I was gonna do it.
I wish I could get that attitude back.
Hold it up! That's crap.
That is dog shit crap.
Why do you have to do something
unnecessarily?
If you're the captain over here,
William-- Look at me!
right you could have gone all the way.
What was that crap,
the shovel pass?
There's never any point in our school,
where we just play, outright, you know.
Remember, think about the ball game
on the way to the game.
[players chattering and laughing]
Marshall began it's season well,
winning 4 of 6.
Today's game will be their first
against the city power.
The only way you got to beat them is
playing good basketball.
All that bullshit that you've playing,
you play half of the game,
for 2-3 minutes you play pretty good,
then you're going to slip.
You have to play the whole ballgame.
[crowd cheering]
When we start, you have to be
completely in the ballgame.
As the game progresses,
and you digress.
By half-time Marshall trails
highly favored Dunbar by 15 points.
But late in the 4th quarter, Arthur
and the Commandos crawl their way back.
On a crucial possession,
the ball goes to Arthur.
[crowd applauding]
[players chattering]
♪ [music] ♪
Led by William's 16 points a game,
the Chargers have 20-3 record,
but coach Pingatore feels they're not
ready for the impending playoffs.
[coach shouting]
Don't hold the ball!
Jesus! Will you cut it out!
You act like a baby.
You are quick crying?
This team just drives me crazy.
We struggle all year.
You think you're better
than you are.
The two big guys are prima donnas.
They should be killing people.
For you people, I'm really agonizing.
And I just hate all that stuff
and all the hollering.
If you don't make it in time,
it will be over next week.
So you won't have to worry about it.
That's the point.
I wanna end this game
in the next 3-4 minutes,
otherwise it is going to be a ballgame.
Alright! Let's go get 'em!
Come on!
Alright, let's go!
William is just too nice of a kid.
I don't know if he has
the killer temperament.
I don't know if he has the eye
of the tiger.
He's gonna need that,
when he goes to the next level.
This business, it's big bucks,
but that's what the scholarship's for.
The day she was gonna, you know,
be born, I told him had to be there.
I don't care where he was at.
I know the game was important,
but this was more important.
His coach doesn't see it like that.
I just can't miss a game
just because, you know,
an incident occurred, unless it's
a death or something like that.
This is once in a lifetime.
Do you think our girl is born every day?
That time of the year too?
State tournament?
That was just simply out of question.
He tells me that will benefits us
in the future. What about now?
Basketball is my ticket
out of the ghetto.
If I haven't been playing ball,
I wasn't even gonna be in college.
I'm going to school, I'm going
to college, and I have a daughter.
The situation's so much different.
- No, it's not!
♪ [music] ♪
[William laughing]
I haven't been working for about a year.
If it wasn't for Norm and Ms.Weir,
I wouldn't even be here.
Cuz when I walked in the door,
the first thing I see on the sign is
"No open list".
It ain't much better to the person
without a college degree it can get.
So I feel like I'll be here
for quite awhile.
I don't believe to people when they
say like: "My school's hard, Man".
The work's hard to me.
If I got to do a report or something,
I don't like none of the topics.
So I just pick something that's simple.
So, what's the topic of your paper?
- The life cycle of the butterfly.
Can you read it for us?
Ooh, come on!
- No, man! I ain't opening it.
I'm just doing this stuff.
I know, but I want to
just hear how you write.
As the people bloom into
another year, you know,
the year change, January 1st.
The butterfly also blooms.
The butterflies are very beautiful
flying objects.
And then I say,
at the beginning of the butterfly,
it goes through a change and all that.
Then I keep going, man.
I do that stuff, I just keep going on
and on and on.
And I'll never stop.
[students shouting]
[movie voice] It's botanical name is
cannabis sativa.
Millions of Americans break the law
and use it.
Arthur's latest report card shows,
he's failing both Spanish and science.
He rushes through his work.
As you see, he just missed
one assignment here.
Okay, his test score is pretty low.
Will you do me a favor?
When you see him slipping like this,
you give me a call and let me know.
I'll make sure I write down
your number.
So I can stay upon topic, because
he tells you one thing--
By the way your book.
Well, we don't have to work on it.
He's probably on the border line.
And they're clowning people.
Just give him the half.
That's what I want you to--
I'm gonna step on it behind
this time.
For his transcript and he got
the transcript.
And he ain't doing that?
We ain't gonna have it like that.
Man, do you remember I told you
about that style I finish.
I don't like some people I know.
I don't need nobody push me.
All I gotta do is have a goal
and a motivation and I'm ready.
It's Sheila's graduation day from
the nurses assistance class
at a local community center. A high grade
will assure her certification.
I want to be a RA nurse.
I've always had that dream.
Ms. Agee.
Sheila, you scored 89 at the exam
and you're gonna get
the IS grade point average.
Really? Really?
I love you, I love you,
I love you.
I'm so happy, I'm so happy.
Oh, thank you Ms.Smart.
Ooh, thank you.
You're so good.
[Sheila crying]
[indistinct chattering]
You really inspired me to go on.
Not just stop right here, but go far.
And people told me, I won't be able
to do a thing.
♪ [woman singing] ♪
The gym is packed for today's game
against west side rival Westinghouse.
Marshall has rebounded from
last year's dismal record 9-16 record,
to go 16 and 6.
And Arthur has emerged as Commandos'
second leading scorer and assist man.
Some junior colleges have begun to notice.
A lot of these kids won't talk
to a junior college.
Really until after they've seen
the dream of, you know,
Illinois, Nevada, Las Vegas
and Georgetown kinda fade.
The junior college could be
Arthur's only hope.
Without better grades
and 18 on the ACT,
major colleges can't
offer him a scholarship.
It's just too bad those kids
don't realize,
that if they had an 18,
the door is so much wider open.
In the 4th quarter the Commandos
fight back an 11 point half-time deficit.
They trail by 1.
Defense!
[crowd applauding]
Derek Zinnelman's layup pushes
Marshall to a 1 point lead.
Moments later, a Westinghouse foul
and a then a double technical
puts Arthur on the line
with a chance to ice the victory.
The upset victory is a sweet vindication
for the unranked Commandos.
[crowd celebrating]
Arthur Agee, you lead the bunch.
You got seven.
Seven turnovers.
Even for our guy, it's too many.
This is a good win for you,
but it doesn't mean anything.
You got to do better than that.
You gotta do better than that.
Yo Man,
that was a good game though.
You could have played better though,
you know.
[laughing]
You know your mother's
proud of you, don't you?
You did get down,
like a real star.
Nearly four years after discovering
Arthur on the playground,
Earl Smith shows up to see Arthur
win his first playoff game.
I figured, this game
and the next game maybe
his last high school ballgame.
Where have you been, Man?
Where I've been?
I've been working.
Oh yeah, right.
- I've been right here on the playground.
Oh yeah.
- Are you impressed or something?
Yeah, I'm impressed. I'm here.
If I wasn't impressed,
I wouldn't have followed you.
You've been talking things?
- For what?
You want to talk to my mom?
Why not?
What do I have to talk to her about?
I don't know.
- You ain't there.
I had a breakdown.
I was thinking about going tonight
to see St. Joe's play.
But I wasn't sure you have time to do it.
Yeah.
I've got a bitter taste in my mouth
about a lot of things that had happened.
A lot of people accused me of taking
youngsters out there in the city
and take them out
to the St. Joe's high school
and they asked what did I
get out of the deal.
And a lot of racial slurs
and so forth from our own people
about me and what I did.
I still felt and feel that I was doing
the right thing for that particular time.
Sometimes I have second thoughts
when I see the end results
and what happened to the youngsters.
Arthur...Arthur Agee, sophomore.
Oh my Gosh, what are you doing?
What are you doing here?
I'm going to school.
- Where?
Marshall.
I talk to you, can you believe it?
Good. So you're here just to see
the Patriots playing the St.Joe's?
Yeah.
Arthur! Arthur!
What's up, man?
You've grown up.
Are you playing basketball or what?
What you guys do?
- We are still playing.
What's your next game?
- We gonna play Creighton High School.
William is benched for arriving late
for the locker room...and Nazareth prep.
William enters the to go head-to-head
with Nazareth's star Sean Pearson,
his friend and roommate
from the Nike camp.
The favorite Chargers race
to an early 14 point lead
in the second round playoff game.
But near the end of the game
St. Joe's begins to unravel.
William takes control.
Pearson responds.
His three point shot gives
the Road Runners
their first lead of the game.
For the Chargers, their whole season
may come down to this possession.
Down by 1 with just over
a minute remaining,
a loss tonight will be their earliest exit
from the playoffs in six years.
And for William, there is no next year.
No more chances to go downstate.
[crowd shouting]
[crowd celebrating]
Only one thing...
Bad coaching...bad coaching.
We got in here about five minutes late.
So what?
[indistinct]
Are you crying, man?
How are ya doing?
I don't know.
It's my last year.
I was striving for the same thing.
I'm gonna call you, Man.
- Alright.
I'm gonna be alright. I love you, boy.
- I love you too, Man.
He was twelve minutes late.
The team was dressed and already talking.
And then he comes rolling in.
Maybe he has to learn
something from that.
Even at the game.
The game was a mirror, it was
a mirror of all the games all year.
To quote Isiah, the toughest loss
he ever took was my toughest,
that was the Luther South game in 1979
when we got beat at the buzzer,
on a thirty footer! And we were
the favorite to win the state that year.
Now when I look back at it,
it's one of those great moments
in our high school scene.
My toughest loss to take
when we talk about it.
So that's the way I look,
you know, at these things now.
Arthur, I could have used you tonight.
- Yeah.
Good luck in your quest.
And don't forget, stay in touch.
We can talk about,
you know, school.
Yeah.
I'm watching your score.
How are your grades?
They're alright.
- Good.
We'll miss you.
- I'll miss ya all too.
Well, I'm proud of what you've done.
Mr. Bedford said a lot
of good things about you.
You be in touch, okay?
Good luck!
♪ [music] ♪
[audience applauding]
Marshall's second round opponent
Manly presents little challenge.
It just explains a little bit
about our program.
Where our program's headed.
I like what I'm seeing and I want him
close to home, you know?
I'm kinda leaning your way
because I just thank God that
he's getting to,you know,
somebody that do want him.
I'm the assistant coach.
Nice to meet you.
Arthur Hester.
- I appreciate that.
I'm over at Candy Kane.
- Candy Kane, okay.
May the best man win.
I thought mom was a cheerleader.
- Oh, thanks.
Thank you for the compliment.
His passing--
I think he may pass the ACT.
He may what?
- He may pass.
Well, I hope he does.
Those arches gotta stick together.
- Yeah.
Hey, would you get signed up if
a college coach came up and talk to you?
Not really.
You're just going to another level
of basketball, that's all.
I'll be excited when I get there.
I guess you'll be excited
the whole year.
I'll be excited as soon
as I step up in there.
First day of practice.
If I graduate I gotta be going on
for my family and finish college.
Me too.
In the fourth round against
the heavily favored Cath,
Marshall meet their first true test
of the playoffs.
But the Commandos have been
bugging the odds all year.
Arthur plays one of his best games
of the season, scoring 19 points,
and the Commandos claim a spot
in the city semi-finals.
[crowd celebrating]
Out of round four. I told ya we're
going all the way. All the way!
Is your team afraid of any team
in this city?
On any given day we'll play anybody.
We can beat anybody.
Marshall now faces the ultimate test.
King High School.
The rulers of the public league.
Winners of last year's state crown,
they were labeled
"the best team in the country".
King has fought controversy
by out-recruiting rivals
for the biggest and best
grammar school players.
We don't understand, what we were
really doing to this young kid.
The kid is 12 years old...
You're baiting him to come to your school,
you know, to play basketball.
I'm not going to start recruiting
in that manner.
I'll probably get out of the game
before that.
[cheerleaders singing]
King's strategy is to go inside
to it's two 7 foot starters.
Only Arthur seems unintimidated
by the Jaguars.
The King's poor play
keeps the game close.
I bet they can take 'em.
But in the second half,
King makes their move.
King grabs a 4 point lead.
[coach shouting]
[Arthur's mother shouting]
The Commandos get aggressive
on defense...
...and use their superior speed
on offense.
[coach Bedfod] Sit down!
We have three minutes to go. Sit down!
Marshall grabs a 6 point lead,
late in the game.
[coach Bedford]
We got a long time to play.
Coach Bedford wants to force King
out of their zone defense
and make their big slow players
match up man-to-man
against Marshall's quick guards.
Arthur simply holds the ball
as the clock ticks away.
The King coach has no choice.
[crowd applauding]
For the defending national champions,
it's all over.
And unranked Marshall will play
for the city title.
[players celebrating]
I told you we can do it.
I told you you were going all the way.
I told you-- All the way.
They got the best shot out of him,
you know.
It is great. That was a great shot.
But this in the Tribune
is what I really like.
To Arthur Agee.
Stood as still as a statue.
Time, after all, was on his side.
The championship that I missed
when I was in high school.
21 years later I got a chance to get us
a championship through him.
You know, you always try to build
your children up the same way
you grew up but you're really relying
on the inside...
But this makes you even more confident,
because if he's sure of himself,
you know that you can back off.
Yesterday when he won the game,
you know,
he told me he loved me.
I haven't heard that in a--
You know, you can feel it, but I haven't
heard it coming verbally from him.
In a rematch with the rival Westinghouse
Marshall proves to everybody
they have what it takes
to be city champs.
[commentator] And the Marshall Commandos
have won the public league championship,
in convincing fashion, 58 - 38 winners
over the Westinghouse Warriors.
[players celebrating]
Your ACT came in wherein
you receive a 14, for composite,
which is not high enough.
You have taken the test now...
this is the fourth time. If you add
all those up,
it comes up to 17.2.
In order to play at Marquette
you have to get the 18
and I'm very very concerned.
One assistant called twice this week
and Bo Ellis called today.
Smile William,
it's not the end of the world, right?
I hope not.
Well, you gotta work at this as hard
as you work on your jumpshot.
And it was missing a lot this year.
Now you're down to the final inning
and the last strike.
[cheerleaders singing]
What are we going to be?
- [crowd] State champion.
[players chattering]
♪ [music] ♪
[crowd cheering]
Downstate, Marshall plays it's
familiar role as underdog
with the 3rd rank at the table.
In the media glare of a statewide
audience, Marshall shows big game jitters.
You gotta make the easy shots!
I can't shoot for you.
[commentator] He's gonna penetrate,
left it for Christian...missed the shot.
Luther Bedford looks like he's ready
to commit suicide over there.
[Arthur's mother shouting]
[commentator] Now in the corner...
get in there.
But in the 3rd quarter,
the Commandos charge back.
[commentator] Now steal by Marshall,
Agee will take it all the way.
Yes! That's the way you go.
[commentator] Marshall's first lead
since the 1st quarter.
Like a lightning ball,
the Commandos have struck.
37 -36 Marshall lead--
I've always been dreaming like,
me and William,
taking 'em downstate together.
When I was at St. Joseph's,
maybe we coulda win downstate,
may be we couldn't,
but he did, my Man in Marshall.
Arthur's big 4th quarter helps
to add Batavia
to Marshall's growing list of upsets.
In the post-game news conference,
coach Bedford labels
his unranked team
"the giant killers".
You're playing the number one team,
we're playing the number two team.
This is the first time in the history
of the school, that we've gone this far.
Really?
- In the history of the school--
- It's like Commando...to be an underdog,
I'm glad that we are,
because that will show you
how you could come up.
And there you beat your opponent.
[laughing]
Oh yeah.
That's a good place for Man to come.
This is a really something that
our child...wouldn't really miss at all.
Like a whole different world.
It's beyond different.
This is the final game. We'll see
some great individuals.
Just as we saw many years ago.
Remember Isiah Thomas,
One of the great guys. There you see
the same moves
he plays with in the NBA today.
Well, we have someone like that.
Howard Nathan, number 34 for Manual.
Marshall got here because
of one thing -- quickness.
The reason -- Arthur Agee.
Look at this man, he just explodes.
He can get downcourt as quick
as anyone as I have ever seen.
In the semi-finals,
Arthur goes head-to-head
with Howard Nathan,
the All-American.
Make him work for it, Man!
Make him work for what he gets.
All the way, let's go!
All the way, Man. All the way.
Yeah, that's the way.
That's it, that's it.
[commentator] Arthur Agee,
spinning inside tough shot...good!
Arthur has a great first half,
but the Rams play even better.
[cheerleaders singing]
In the second half Arthur tries
to pick up where he left off.
But it's the Rams who don't
miss a beat,
pressing the tempo against
the tired Commandos.
[coach speaking]
[commentator] Marshall showed us
last night
they have the ability to come back.
Let's see what they can do here.
This is Nathan...nice pass...
A great run for Luther Bedford's team.
And a foul on Agee,
he fouls out.
He just never quit,
he kept going for the basketball.
I wouldn't be surprised, if he made
the All-Tournament team tonight.
Number one...still number one.
Though they lose to Manual,
they finish third in the state.
The highest the Marshall team
has finished since 1960.
This was a great season you had.
There is nothing sweeter than going
downstate as a young person.
I mean the records gonna
stay there, you know.
1991 is the team for Marshall play
and you are part of that.
That's a part of history.
Best wishes to all you seniors
and whatever you're trying to do,
as you know I'll be there
around school, as we always are.
I can help you,
if you want to be helped.
25 games, it ain't 30,
and keep touching that up.
Like coach said, you just
have to sacrifice, you know,
sacrifice everything you have.
Like give love to the game of basketball,
just get out there and give
all your heart.
He's gotta little ways to go,
but he's gonna get there.
Hopefully he's got his head
screwed on pretty good, you know?
And now he's gonna be
on his own, to do whatever.
Hopefully he'll do it right.
When we got down here,
people didn't respect Marshall.
And they're looking like:
"Who do they got on their team?"
And I just had come to out
and prove myself who I was.
I've been playing Division I basketball,
cuz all I need is just a scholarship.
That's all I'm living for.
All these areas here are our
computer labs.
I'll take you through all those rooms.
Arthur's first recruiting visit takes him
to a junior college in Southern Missouri.
The strength I see here is
the tremendous teaching
that goes on here. Have you decided
what you want to be going to?
Communications.
Are you more interested
in the overall communications?
I like that and accounting, like business.
- Okay.
We enjoy winning things,
but the primary purpose is your education.
How far goes your curriculum's mess?
I wanna fall back like I have
my own business, just like a real estate.
You tried on it?
It's about $120 a piece.
You need to be very careful
with this decision.
Two years of your college finished,
the scholarship
to a divisional university,
exactly where you'd wanna be
on track to graduate in four years.
♪ [music] ♪
Mineral Area doesn't have dorms,
but it does have a basketball house.
All the ballplayers
on scholarship live here.
[students chattering]
Of the seven blacks in the entire school,
six live in this house.
You come in and look
at this little house,
then after awhile,
you get used to it.
Trying to make a little home,
you know?
I'm away from home anyway.
We hang around each other
most of the time.
You know who to trust
and not to trust.
I just want to go somewhere
I'm gonna play.
I'll get the grades.
A little basketball.
How many players that leave there
and then go to a four year college?
31 sophomores in a row.
Really?
Hey. how are you doing?
Bo and Sheila have been separated.
She asked him to return today
over Arthur's objections.
I'll show you exactly what
scholarship entails.
Is this a full scholarship
for the two years?
The reason I'm skeptical is because
of a promise that was made in the past.
From the time he comes down
until he leaves,
he will not have a financial need.
Now, when you make this decision,
you got to live and die with it.
Cuz it's your decision to make.
Now I'm here to support you,
if you don't search this whole thing.
And it's what you really want,
not, you know, cuz mama said so.
Cuz you save your mama money,
because if we have to,
we'll still pay if you have to try to pay.
I'm just saying...
I understand what you're saying.
You want to save somebody money.
But still--
But he gotta still do
what's best for him.
But still you want the best for you,
even you have to
or we have to go in a hole,
you know?
You know what I'm saying,
I'm just saying now,
still the decision is up to you.
Are you signing?
- Yeah. Yup.
Let's do it now.
♪ [music] ♪
What time is it?
Come on, Bo!
Wag the dog!
You wanna see it rain?
Let it rain!
[Bo and William chattering]
Like father, like son.
What's up with that?
You better stick to church music,
this basketball is old.
[spectators shouting]
[Arthur and Bo arguing]
Your mama ain't here
to get you the ball.
Give me the rock.
- Let's make it rain! Make it rain!
Bang! Right there.
It's raining, Bo.
It's raining.
[Bo arguing]
Good evening, Ladies and Gentlemen,
and welcome
to St.Joseph's Annual
Basketball Awards Dinner.
We had a difficult year.
Most of you are aware of that...
[William] When I first went to St. Joe's,
I really did eat, sleep and drink
basketball. That's all I did.
But it became more of a job
than a sport to play.
And then coach Pingatore
just had these dreams in his head.
He just wanted me to go
the same route he took Isiah.
Basketball was just like...
he's possessed with it,
you know, it's his life. And he wanted it
to be everybody else's life too.
...All-Conference in the ACC,
All-State in the Suntimes,
MacDonald All-American nomination,
MVP 1990-91 season...William Gates!
[audience applauding]
And I had some real problems.
I couldn't go at none of them about it.
I was having some problems
with Canton family and my family,
and I said: "You know coach Pingatore,
they've finally been getting on me,
about, you know, I'm not doing this,
I'm not doing that".
The only thing coach Pingatore
could say is: "Write them off".
That's all he told me.
I was like: "What kind of advice is that?"
What does it feel...to be finishing?
Don't say anything
you don't mean, William!
I'm serious, coach.
I mean, we had run-ins and--
- Who had run-ins?
Me and you.
- We did?
Like that time you made me
run 75 stairs.
You'll never forget that?
So you should have been happy and
enthusiastic about doing your punishment.
But someday you're gonna learn that
everything that was done
was for your benefit.
So that you come back four years
from now and say:
"Coach, you were right.
Everything that happened at St.Joe's
helped me a lot and as a result
I got a degree".
That's what I'm hoping for.
I'm going into a communication,
so when you start asking for a donation,
I'll know a way to turn you down.
I'm sure you'll never turn us down.
I never really felt that
he bought into the system.
He was never convinced, what he
was doing was the right thing to do.
Pull over all he had a good career,
not a great career.
Could have been different
if the injury didn't occur.
But it did occur.
And that was the big difference.
I used to expect that
you'd do a lot better.
I don't want this to be the highlight
of your career.
You got a lot of bigger,
better things to do.
I'll see you later.
Good luck!
Well, another one walks out the door
and another one comes in the door.
That's what's all about.
♪ [music] ♪
You can't do it for me.
I got the score I needed.
Alright.
- Hey.
Algebra...It's one of the greatest
feelings in the world.
After five attempts, William's composite
score of 17.5 is rounded up to 18,
and he can finally accept
the scholarship to play at Marquette.
♪ [music] ♪
I think my mom,
all through high school,
really really was proud of me.
She said: "Everybody's storing
their dreams into you,
but you gotta throw
your own dreams into yourself".
And when I gave her the diploma
after the graduation, she was like:
"This is it. My proudest moments".
[chattering]
Curtis always wanted to go
to Marquette, and his grades
weren't good enough for him to go.
And now he's back, he got the grades.
[teacher] One, two countries are we
competing with--
Before Arthur can graduate,
he must have summer school.
And for the first time in three years,
Shannon isn't there with him.
He thought he could sell drugs
and don't get caught, you know?
But he found out the hard way.
And I told him,
while he was doing all that
I don't want to hang with Shannon in.
I was like: 'Shannon, you should stop,
stop doing this to her".
We always say, we will never do
stuff like that.
We're just gonna graduate
and going to college.
But you know, he had to be the one.
One week before his graduation,
Arthur is robbed at gunpoint.
At first I thought he's gonna shoot me
because I had no money.
Because he kept asking me: "You've got
some money? Where your wallet at?"
Like: "Why are you trying
to act like this?"
And I like: "I ain't got no wallet".
That day, you know,
he grabbed me and stuff.
And I was...I was about to panic
and stuff...
...and I just calmed down.
I sat down and had
a long talk with him and his sister.
Someone put a pistol on her, right down
in the street in front the house.
I said: "Do you all understand what is
going on out here in these streets today?"
Even with me, when I was out there,
you know, out there strung out,
I looked for somebody that
they seemed like they had something.
After you, serg.
I'm ready. I'm ready to leave.
Ain't nobody up here, that's going to jail
on dealing drugs. Or deal--
♪ [music] ♪
I never thought he'd get to the place,
he's at now.
Arthur was really dragged
from of St. Joseph.
That's what you've asked about it.
No matter where you go,
it's what you have in your heart
that you're gonna go somewhere.
[audience applauding]
[people chattering]
♪ [music] ♪
It's scary, man. I'm telling you.
Scary generation, man.
To my son! I hope you
foresee all your dreams
and your desires
that you have within you.
I love you very much!
God, we are thanking
for this day, Lord.
And we ask you to go to junior, Lord.
We thank you, Lord.
Go with him as he tries to better
his education, Lord.
And we thank you for coming
this far.
We came this far by faith, Lord.
And we ask you father, when he get
in college to keep him, Lord.
Keep him protected.
We thank you, Father Jesus.
In Jesus' name we pray. Amen!
Amen!
[chattering and laughing]
I just hope he'd stay in there.
That worries me most.
Once he get indoor,
he won't be staying for lease.
You think he gonna make it?
I think he gonna make it.
Oh, I hope so anyway.
[woman weeping]
♪ [music] ♪
When I was young, when I was little,
I always used think about the NBA.
If I set my mind,
I can go. I can start and go.
Even to a good college I can go.
But if I don't, you know,
ain't no be drug dealer,
ain't no crap about, you know,
stick up gas stations,
and nothing like that, you know.
I'll probably go to a comedian
or an architect, someone like that.
[cameraman] You don't think that
you'll have the kind of tough times
like your dad's been through?
No. I can't say that I will.
I can't say that I won't. I don't know.
♪ [music] ♪
Four years ago, that's all I used to
dream about was playing in the NBA,
I don't really dream about it
like that anymore.
Even though I love playing basketball
but I wanna other things with my life too.
[phone call replaying]
If I had to stop playing basketball
right now I think I'd still be happy.
I think I would.
That's why when somebody say:
"When you get to the NBA
you'll forget about me"
and all that stuff.
I should say them: "If I don't make it,
won't you forget about me?"
♪ [music] ♪